Guide to the Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools records, 1980-2008 MS2306
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools records
1980-2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Washington Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights and Urban Affairs
MS2306
11.5 Linear Feet 23 document boxes
This collection contains published and unpublished materials such as reports, correspondence, studies, clippings, testimony, financial information, and notebooks, which document the work of Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools from 1980 to 2008. Major topics covered include school conditions, school budgets, school closings, and teacher evaluations and pay. These records were created as part of the organization's work advocating for improvements in the Washington, D.C. public schools.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Projects, reports, and testimony; Clippings; Fundraising and events; Subject files; and Administrative files.
Biographical / Historical
Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools was an advocacy group formed in 1980 to improve the quality of D.C. public schools. It began as a project of the Washington Lawyers' Committee, a pro bono legal services organization focusing on the needs of the poor, including employment, housing, and quality public education. As the District of Columbia faced a school budget crisis in 1980, the Washington Lawyers' Committee assembled a diverse set of parents from both poor and affluent neighborhoods in the city to form Parents United. Member schools at one point represented all eight wards and a majority of D.C.'s regular public schools.
By testifying before the DC Council and Congress, holding meetings, sponsoring fundraising events, and issuing high-profile reports, the group rallied enough public support to increase the budget for city schools in the early 1980s. They also pressed for increases in teacher salaries, implementation of teacher evaluations, universal pre-kindergarten classes, and improvements in school conditions. The organization continued to testify before the D.C. City Council through 2009.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Washington Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights and Urban Affairs, 2012 (2012.052).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains published and unpublished materials such as reports, correspondence, studies, clippings, testimony, financial information, and notebooks, which document the work of Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools from 1980 to 2008. Major topics covered include school conditions, school budgets, school closings, and teacher evaluations and pay. These records were created as part of the organization's work advocating for improvements in the Washington, D.C. public schools.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Schools -- Washington (D.C.); Washington Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights and Urban Affairs
- Projects, reports, and testimony, 1980-2008; Series 1; 2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains reports, newsletters, written testimonies, surveys, studies, and proposals produced by Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools from 1980 to 2008. Major topics covered include school conditions, school budgets, and teacher evaluations and pay.
  - Business and Civic Leader Study of the Fiscal Needs of the D.C. Public Schools, 1985; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Campaign for Human Development [1 of 2], 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campaign for Human Development [2 of 2], 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campaign for Human Development, 1988; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Congressional lobbying, 1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Public Schools: Where Does the Money Go?, 1991; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Public School Initiative, 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - KPMG study staff recommendations, 1989; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - KPMG study update, 1989; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal Constraints on Decentralization in the Public School System of the District of Columbia, 1976; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Merit pay proposal, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Parents United focus group meetings, 1993-1994; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Parents United newsletter, 1991-1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Parents United Public School Handbook and Honor Roll, 1996-1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Parents United reports, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Parents United testimony before the finance committee of the Board of Education, 1994; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Parents United/Washington Parent Group Fund Enrichment Development Project, 1988-1989; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Press releases, 1980-1992; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Principal/Parent Exchange (Enrichment Development Project), 1988; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Project accountability, 1997-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Recruitment and Retention of Excellent Teachers for the District of Columbia Public Schools, 1987; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations for the Teacher Evaluation System, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Report card, 1987; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - School building survey [1 of 2], 1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - School building survey [2 of 2], 1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - School buildings report, 1991; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - School conditions survey, 1986-1987; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - School priorities survey, 1997; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The School Reform Debate, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Survey of D.C. Principals, 1988; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Survey of school resources, 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Survey of School Building Conditions [1 of 2], 1987; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Survey of School Building Conditions [2 of 2], 1987; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Testimony before the D.C. City Council, 1994; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Testimony before the D.C. City Council, 1995; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Washington Parent Group Fund Enrichment Development Program, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - What Happened to the Teacher Pay Raise, 1993; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Clippings, 1981-2000; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
  This series contains clippings of articles about Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools and related school reform topics. They date from 1981 to 2000.
  Arranged chronologically except for certain files, which are titled and arranged by topic.
  - D.C. Board of Education clippings, 1995; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1983; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1983-1987; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1995-1996; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings [1 of 2], 1997; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings [2 of 2], 1997; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings -- asbestos, 1984; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings -- Initiative 25, 1987; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings -- referendum, 2000; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings -- special education, 1995-2000; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper editorials, 1981; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper editorials, 1990; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Parents United clippings, reports, and history, 1981-1983; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Parents United clippings, reports, and history, 1990-1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Fundraising and events, 1981-1997; Series 3; 2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
  Arranged alphabetically by name of event or funder.
  This series contains correspondence, press releases, photographs, and grant materials documenting fundraising events hosted by Parents United for the D.C. Public Schools and foundations supporting the fundraising goals of the organization. Materials date from 1981 to 1997. Major topics include the Key to the City road race fundraising event and the 10th Anniversary Gala celebrating Parents United's first decade.
  - 10th Anniversary Gala, 1990; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 10th Anniversary Gala book, 1990; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 10th Anniversary Gala book photos, 1990; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Advocacy awards, 1991-1994; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - April Trust, 1985; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - ARCA Foundation (ARLP), 1989; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Citicorp Savings of Washington, 1988; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Edna McConnell Clark Foundation, 1988; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Combined Federal Campaign, 1995; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Field Foundation, 1984-1985; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Fiscal planning, 1990-1991; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - General fundraising materials, 1997; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Edward W. Hazen Foundation, 1983; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Paul and Annetta Himmelfarb Foundation, 1988; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Hitachi Foundation, 1988; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Key to the City, 1988; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Key to the City, 1989; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Key to the City, 1988-1990; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Key to the City, 1991; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Key to the City, 1993; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Key to the City correspondence, 1990; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Key to the City correspondence, 1991; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Key to the City correspondence, 1992; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Key to the City correspondence, 1990-1993; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Key to the City permit and sponsors, 1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Key to the City photographs, 1989; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Open House, 1995; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - New World Foundation, 1981; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Washington Parent Group Fund, 1983-1984; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Subject files, 1980-2001; Series 4; 5 Linear Feet 10 document boxes
  This series contains correspondence, reports, testimony, financial materials, data, maps, questionnaires, and transcripts documenting education reform efforts in Washington, D.C. from 1980 to 2001. Major topics include Washington, D.C.'s public schools budget, the Goals 2000 state education plan, school closings, and teacher salaries and evaluations. Unlike materials in the other series in this collection, these materials are not primarily about (or produced by) Parents United, but represent topics of interest to school reformers during this period.
  - Beginning Teacher Testing, 1988; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Budget correspondence with Congress, 1982; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Budget hearings and testimony, 1980-1981; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Candidate questionnaire, 1990-1992; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 1 resources, 1993; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 1 -- language minority students, 1993; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Charter schools, 1993-1997; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Citizens for the D.C. Public School Initiative, 1987; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Citizens Hearing on D.C. School Budget Priorities, undated; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Classroom photos, undated; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Comparative analysis -- D.C. and Montgomery County School Systems, 1981; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - COPE, 1996; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Commission on Consensus Reform, 1996; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - COPE budget report, 1992; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - COPE rightsizing report, 1994; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Curriculum audit, 1992; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - DCPS budget, 1981; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - DCPS budget, 1982-1983; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - DCPS budget, 1991; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - DCPS budget, 1995; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - DCPS budget, 1996; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - DCPS budget, 1998; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - DCPS budget, 1999; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - DCPS budget, 2000; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - DCPS capital improvement projects, 1998; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - DCPS Educational Technology Plan, 1996-1997; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - DCPS job cuts, 1995; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - DCPS per-pupil funding, 1993-1999; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - DCPS personnel, 1992; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - DCPS Reports, 1982-1985; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - DCPS school maps, 1983-1991; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - D.C. City Council, 1995; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - D.C. City Council budget reports, 1987-1996; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - D.C. City Council candidate questionnaire, 1984; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Questions to D.C. City Council, 1995; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Education Plan, 1993; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Excess teachers, 1998-1999; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Fire codes, 1994; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Goals 2000, 1994-1998; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Goals 2000, 1998; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Goals 2000 -- DCPS implementation, 1997; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Goals 2000 DOE monitoring, 1996-1998; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Goals 2000 facilities planning, 1996; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Goals 2000 input documents, 1996; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Goals 2000 panel membership, 1996; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Goals 2000 -- Phase II, 2000-2001; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Goals 2000 presentations, 1995-1996; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Goals 2000 Technology Task Force, 1995; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Goals 2000 -- Washington D.C. Community Plan for Educational Improvement, 1997; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Goals 2000 Working Groups, 1997; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Initiative 25, 1987; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Institute for Responsive Education, 1985; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - International Baccalaureate, 1997; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law financial, 1982; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Literature on race, class, and schools, 1980-1986; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Lobbying regulations, 1983-1984; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Local School Restructuring Teams, 1995-1996; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Mayor's Advisory Committee on Board of Education Appointments, 2000; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan school data, 1983-1984; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - New School Leadership Committee, 2000; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Nurses, 1997; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Parent involvement, 1989; Series 4 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Office of Campaign Finance, 2000; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Parent/School Partnership, 1997; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - PTA history, 1989-1997; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Per-pupil funding, 1996; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Pupil-teacher ratios [1 of 2], 1989; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Pupil-teacher ratios [2 of 2], 1989; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Report to the Mayor, 1981; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Research on other school systems, 1997-1998; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - A Review of Parent Empowered Choice Programs, 1986; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - School closings, 1996; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - School closings [1 of 3], 1997; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - School closings [2 of 3], 1997; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - School closings [3 of 3], 1997; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - School closing reports [1 of 4], 1992-1997; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - School closing reports [2 of 4], 1992-1997; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - School closing reports [3 of 4], 1992-1997; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - School closing reports [4 of 4], 1992-1997; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - School reform, 1995-1996; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - School security, 1985; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - School-based Management, 1989; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Special education, 1991-1999; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Special education complaints, 1993-1999; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Tax credit -- Initiative No. 7, 1981; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Teach for America, 1993; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Teacher appraisal process, 1981; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Teacher certification, 1983; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Teacher certification -- legal issues, 1983; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Teacher certification requirements, 1977; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Teacher competency/testing, 1981-1984; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Teacher evaluation, 1982; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Teacher evaluation -- AFT, 1981; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Teacher evaluation in Canada, 1982; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Teacher evaluation -- use in RIFs, 1982; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Teacher recruitment and retention, 1987; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Teacher residency requirements, 1988; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Teacher salaries, 1986-1987; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Teacher salaries, 1997-1998; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Test scores, 1986-1991; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Town Hall, 1992; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Transcript -- D.C. Board of Education community meeting, 1989; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Tuition Tax Credit Initiative, undated; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Turner Elementary School education project, undated; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Turner Elementary School parent group fund, 1986-1987; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Vocational education, 1985; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Vocational education, 1996; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Walker Jones Elementary, 1998; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Ward I Council, 1983; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Ward III Task Force, 1982; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Ward IV community meeting, 1981; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Ward VI Education Watch, 1981; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 15)
- Administrative files, 1980-2004; Series 5; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  This series contains correspondence, financial information, legal documents, notebooks, and information on Parents United representatives, programs, and services. The material dates from 1980-2004. Primary correspondents include Delabian Rice-Thurston, director of Parents United from 1984 to 2000, and Mary Levy, budget analyst and counsel for Parents United and Washington Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights. Notebooks contain notes kept by Delabian Rice-Thurston from 1988 through 1997.
  - 990 forms, 1998-2001; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Bank statements, 1990-1991; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, 1989; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of incorporation, 1982; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Collaboration, 1997; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1998; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- Mary Levy, 1997-2004; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Delabian Rice-Thurston, 1991; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Delabian Rice-Thurston, 1993-1999; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Superintendant and Mayor, 2000-2001; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Exemptions and licenses, 1984-1985; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Incorporation papers, 1982-1988; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - IRS, 1985-1989; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Move to Dupont Circle, 1994; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, 1988-1989; Series 5 (Box 22, Binder 1)
  - Notebook, 1989-1990; Series 5 (Box 22, Binder 2)
  - Notebook, 1990-1991; Series 5 (Box 22, Binder 3)
  - Notebook, 1991-1992; series 5 (Box 22, Binder 5)
  - Notebook, 1992-1994; Series 5 (Box 22, Binder 4)
  - Notebook, 1995-1997; Series 5 (Box 22, Binder 5)
  - Parents United v. Barry, 1996; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Parents United budget, 1980-1987; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Parents United budget, 1991-1995; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Parents United budget, 2000-2001; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Parents United buttons, undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Parents United's programs and services, undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Parents United representatives and member schools, 1982-1986; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Parents United ward coordinators, undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Service charges, 1984-1985; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Standards for Non-Profit Corporations, undated; Series 5 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Steering Committee, 1986-1987; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Tax exemption, 1982-1989; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Washington Lawyers' Committee invoices, 1990; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 19)